Guide to the Incunabula Collection at Stanford University, 1467-1500
Department of Special Collections
- Bernard, of Clairvaux, Saint, 1090 or 91-1153. Opus egregiu[m] Diui Bernardi super Cantica Canticoru[m] Salomonis: tam co[n]templatiue q[uam] actiue vite cultorib[us] precipue vero p[rae]dicatoribus accommodatissimum feliciter incipit / multa diligentia castigatum ac emendatum per Magistru[m] Iohannem Rouauld sacre theologie doctorem. Parisijs impressi: [Georges Wolf], anno Domini [24 Nov. 1494], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1494 .B47; [244] p. (last p. blank); 23 cm.
  References: Copinger 962. GW 3936. Goff (rev.), B-429. Hain-Copinger 2858. ISTC (RLIN), ib00429000. Pellechet 2097.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: 1 initial in red and blue, other initials in red; paragraph marks and underscoring in yellow. Binding: modern sheep; panelled spine with gilt decoration; marbled endpapers. Binder's title: Opus egreg super Cantica Canticorum. Provenance: Philip C. Duschnes ... New York (bookseller's label).
- Cassini, Samuele. Opus quod Liber ysagogicus inscribitur. Impressu[m] Mediola[n]i: [Uldericus Scinzenzeler], anno Christia[n]e salutis [22 Apr. 1494], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1494 .C27; [160] p. (last p. blank): ill.; 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 768 (IA.26747). Goff (rev.), S-118. Hain 13695. Hain-Copinger-Reichling 4567. ISTC (RLIN), is00118000. Pellechet 3343.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): One woodcut initial colored in red. Binding: white boards; gilt decorated. Binder's title: Liber ysagogicus. Provenance: Arthur G. Kennedy (signature).
- Curtius Rufus, Quintus. Uniform title: Quintus Curtius. Title: De rebus gestis Alexandri Magni regis Macedonum. Caption Title: Q. Curtii De rebus gestis Alexandri Magni regis Macedonum liber tertius. Impressit Venetiis: Ioannes de Tridino alias Tacuinus, anno M.cccc.xciiii die xvii Iulii [17 July 1494], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1494 .C87 f; [136] p. (last p. blank); 29 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 528 (IB.24042). Goff (rev.), C-1002. GW 7875. Hain-Copinger, 5885. ISTC, ic01002000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: capitals added in red or blue. Ms. marginalia. Binding: vellum, with title label on spine. Binder's title: Quin: Curt: 1494.
- Johannes, de Lapide, ca. 1425-1496. Resolutoriu[m] dubioru[m] circa celebrat[i]onem missaru[m] occurrentiu[m] / p[er] Venerabile[m] Patre[m] D[omi]n[u]m Iohanne[m] de Lapide ... ex sacroru[m] canonu[m] p[ro]batoru[m]q[ue] docto[rum] sententijs diligenter collectu[m]; su[m]ma dubio[rum] in hoc op[er]e resoluto[rum] CLXVI. Alt title: Resolutorium dubiorum circa celebrationem missarum occurrentium. Alt title: Johannes de Lapide Resolutorium Argentine impressi: P[er] Martinu[m] Flach ..., anno natiuitatis Iesu Christi M cccc xciiij [1494], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1494 .J63; [64] p.; 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., I, p. 153 (IA.2181). Goff (rev.), J-361. Hain-Copinger 9909. ISTC (RLIN), ij00361000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: brown boards, title label on spine. Binder's title: Johannes de Lapide Resolutorium 1494.
- John XXI, Pope, d. 1277. Textus [et] copulata omnium tractatuu[m] Petri Hyspani: etia[m] paruo[rum] logicaliu[m] et tractatus Syncathegorematum que[m] aliqui octauu[m] vocant cu[m] quibusda[m] alijs sagaciter adiunctis / iterum atq[ue] iterum diligentissime correcta [secundu]m doctrinam ... Thome Aquinatis ac iuxta frequens exercitiu[m] magistro[rum] Colonie infra sedecim domos i[n] bursa Montis regentiu[m] in hu[n]c vnu[m] lib[rum] congesta.[Nuremberg: Anton Koberger], 15 June 1494., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1494 .J64; [1], CCLXIX [i.e. CCLXVII], [6] leaves (the last leaf blank); [1], CXLVII leaves: ill. (woodcuts); 23 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 439 (IA.7473). Goff (rev.), J-239. Hain, 8705. ISTC, ij00239000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Variant: last line reads as cited by Hain: Et hec de syncathegorematibus dicta sufficiant. Rubrication: capitals, initial strokes and underscoring added in red, black or yellow; some woodcut initials and illustrations hand-colored; ms. marginalia and fists. Binding: tooled leather over boards, 2 fore- edge clasps (one a replacement). Provenance: inscription on t.p. dated 1546.
- Paolo, Veneto, ca. 1370-1428. Liber posteriorum Magistri Pauli Veneti. Impressum Venetijs: Per Simone[m] Papiense[m] dictu[m] Biuilaqua; Impensis ... Vincentij de Benalis, sexto idus Aprilis 1494 [8 April 1494], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1494 .P26 f; 105, [1] leaves: ill.; 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 519 (IB.23937). Goff (rev.), P-216. Hain-Copinger 12514. ISTC (RLIN), ip00216000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: vellum; brand on foot edge. Variant: Incipit reads: expositio [tu?] libros. Ms. marginalia; trimmed.
- Thomas, Aquinas, Saint, 1225?-1274. Cathena aurea angelici diuiniq[ue] doctoris Sancti Thome de Aquino sacri Ordinis Predicatoru[m]: nuper redacta super o[mn]ia euangelia dominicalia [et] ferialia: necnon super queda[m] de sanctis / per religiosum patre[m] Fratre[m] Petrum de Vincentia sacri eiusde[m] ordinis in alma Venetiarum ciuitate.[Venice: Joannes Rubeus Vercellensis, 29 April 1494], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1494 .T48; [684] (last p. blank) p.; 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 418 (IA.23164). Goff (rev.), T-224. Hain-Copinger, 1337. ISTC (RLIN), it00224000. Pellechet 940.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: blank a1 lacking. Binding: quarter vellum; brown boards; edges speckled red. Binder's title: S. Tomaso Oper[e]. Binding error: [long s] signature bound after s signature. Provenance: ms. marginalia; coat of arms inscribed on pi2r.
- Augustine, Saint, Bishop of Hippo. Sermones Sancti Augustini de tempore.[Basel]: Explicitu[s] est opus ... Basilee p[er] magistru[m] Ioanne[m] de Amerbach, anno salutiferi Virginalis partus nonagesimoquinto supra millesimu[m] quaterq[ue] centesimu[m] [1495], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1495 .A947 f; [512] p.: 1 ill. (woodcut); 33 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 756 (IB.37380). Goff (rev.), A-1308. GW 2920. Hain 2008. ISTC (RLIN), ia01308000. "Annotatio notabiliu[m] sententiaru[m]": 3A2-2D8 (2D8v blank).
  Stanford copy: Sanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: large capital in red and blue;capitals, initials, initial strokes, and paragraph marks in red. T.p. mutilated, with slight loss of upper left corner of illustration on t.p. verso. Binding: blind tooled calf over boards; guards, with ms. text, on upper and lower covers;2 stubs follow final page; metal clasps on upper cover. Binder's title: S. Augustini; in case, with title: Sermones. Provenance: Pro. Conventu Bambergen[sis?] FF. Min. (inscription); ms. marginalia.
- Boccaccio, Giovanni, 1313-1375. Genealogiae Ioannis Boccatii, cum demonstrationibus in formis arborum designatis; eiusdem De montibus syluis, de fontibus, lacubus fluminibus: ac etiam de stagnis paludibus, necnon de maribus, seu diuersis maris nominibus. Alt title: De montibus syluis, de fontibus, lacubus fluminibus. Alt title: Genealogie deorum. Venetiis: Ductu expensis nobilis uiri D. Octauiani Scoti ... finis i[m]positus fuit huic operi per Bonetum Locatellum, M.CCCC.XCIIII. septimo Kalendas Martias [23 Feb. 1495], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1495 .B6 f; 162 leaves: [13] geneal. tables; 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 444 (IB.22904). Goff (rev.), B-753. GW 4478. Hain-Copinger, 3321. ISTC, ib00753000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: blue wrappers; in brown quarter morocco case with title: Boccaccio. Genealogie deorum. 1494. Ms. marginalia.
- Prouerbia Senece. Caption title: Incipiu[n]t Prouerbia Senece s[ecundu]m ordine[m] alphabeti.[Speyer: Konrad Hist, ca. 1495], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1495 .P78; [24] p. (last 3 p. blank); 21 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), S-402. GW (Nachtr.), 322. ISTC (RLIN), is00402000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials, initial strokes, and paragraph marks in red. Imperfect: leaf [b6] (blank) lacking. Unbound. Provenance: Hildebrand Library (ink-stamp).
- Thomas, Aquinas, Saint, 1225?-1274. Diui Thome Aquinatis sacri predicato[rum] ordinis In libros Aristotelis de celo [et] mu[n]do preclarissima co[m]mentaria: cum additionibus Petri de Aluernia eiusdem ordinis.[Venice]: Impressum Venetijs ac studiosissime elaboratum per Gregoriu[m] [et] Ioannem de Gregorijs fratres, 1495 die v[er]o vltimo Octobris [31 Oct.], Call No. Barchas Collection KA1495 .T5; 72 leaves: ill.; 29 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 347 (IB.21105). Goff (rev.) A-979. GW 2356. Hain 1532. ISTC, ia00979000. Klebs 964.3.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Binder: Cav. Dante Gozzi e figlio, Modena (stamp on lower cover). Binding: tooled brown morocco. Binder's title: Aqcuino. Aristotelis Celo et mundo. Provenance: Honeyman sale.
- Vocabularius incipiens Teutonicum ante Latinum.[Haguenau, Heinrich Gran, ca. 1495], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1495 .V63; [384] p. 22 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), V-319. ISTC, iv00319000. GW (Nachtr.) 377.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: lacks final 2 leaves (E7,8). Binding: tooled leather spine, raised bands of heavy cord, wooden boards scored with numbers, remains of fore-edge clasp. In case with title: Vocabularius Teutonicum Latinum. Provenance: Fris Martini Creusuk (inscription); Hospitalis S. Matthei Wratisl. (inscription); Bibliothek [von?] H. Barth in Breslau (ink-stamp); R. Hildebrand (signature); Hildebrand Library (ink-stamp).
- Uniform Title: Bible. Latin. Vulgate. 1496 Title: Biblia cu[m] concordantijs in margine nec no[n] Hebraicoru[m] nominu[m] interpretationibus.[Brescia]: Impressa est hec Biblia ... Angeli [et] Iacobi Britannico[rum] ..., anno ... Mcccclxxxxvi die vero xxix. Decembris [29 Dec. 1496], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1496 .B5; [1008] p. (last 2 p. blank); 19 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), B-599. GW 4276. BM 15th cent., VII, p. 978 (IA.31154). Darlow Moule, 6087. Hain-Copinger 3119. ISTC (RLIN), ib00599000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Imperfect: t.p. wanting; title supplied from BM 15th cent., VII, p. 978 (IA.31154). Binding: full vellum; in case. Binder's title: Biblia Latina.
- Bonaventure, Saint, Cardinal, ca. 1217-1274. Seraphici Doctoris Sancti Bonaue[n]ture Sermones de tempore et sanctis: cum co[m]muni sanctorum. In imp[er]iali ciuitate Haganaw ...: [Henri Gran], anno D[omi]ni Mcccc.xcvj. quinto idus Ianuarij [9 Jan. 1496]., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1496 .B66; [286] leaves (last blank); 23 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 684 (IA.13472). GW 4815. Goff(rev.), B-952. Hain-Copinger, 3520. ISTC (RLIN), ib00952000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: some initial capitals supplied in black ink. Imperfect: a1-b1 mutilated, with some loss of text. Binding: embossed leather over wooden boards; remains of clasps; portions of rubricated sheets with Latin text as stubs at front and back; in box with title: Sermones de tempore et de sanctis. Ms. marginalia, underlining, and fists; extensive ms. annotations on final two leaves.
- Mancinelli, Antonio, 1452-ca. 1505. Mancinelli Veliterni De componendis versibus opusculum / cum additionibus Francisci Mataratij [et] Sulptij [sic] Verulani arti carminu[m] necessarijs.[Leipzig: Wolfgang Stoeckel], anno Domini 1496., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1496 .M34; [52] p. (last 3 p. blank); 21 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), M-148. Hain-Reichling 10615. ISTC (RLIN), im00148000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: headings underscored and some initials added in red. Binding: black marbled wrappers; label marked II on upper cover. Provenance: R. Hildebrand (signature); Hildebrand Library (ink-stamp); ms. underscoring, marginalia and emendations; last blank leaf fully inscribed with Ecomiu[m] Bramatices.
- Petrarca, Francesco, 1304-1374. Librorum Francisci Petrarchae Basileae impressorum annotatio. Impressis Basileae: Per Magistrum Ioannem de Amerbach, anno salutiferi uirginalis partus [1496], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1496 .P383; [778] p. (the last 2 p. blank); 28 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 757 (IB.37389). Goff (rev.), P-365. Hain-Copinger 12749. ISTC (RLIN), ip00365000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): untouched. Binding: gilt red morocco, turn- ins, panelled spine; marbled endpapers; all edges gilt. Binder's title: Petrarchae Opera latine. Basiliae, 1496. Provenance: Roberti Marchionis de Crewe (armorial bookplate); ms. marginalia (trimmed) and underscoring; ms. Latin poem on final blank.
- Pius II, Pope, 1405-1464. Uniform title: De ritu, situ, moribus et conditione Theutonie descriptio Title: Enee Siluij De ritu, situ, moribus et condicione Theutonie descriptio. Title in colophon: De ritu, situ, moribus ac conditione Almanie Opidanu[m] Liptzensem Lyptzick impressum et bene emendatum: Per baccalariu[m] Wolfgangum Stockel de Monaco, anno a natiuitate Cristi [1496] die vero [9] mensis Aprilis., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1496 .P396; 49, [1] leaves (last leaf blank); 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 653 (IA.12175). Goff (rev.), P-744. Hain-Copinger 249. ISTC (RLIN), ip00744000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials, initial strokes and underscoring in red on leaves A1v and A2r only. Imperfect: last blank leaf lacking. Binding: marbled blue wrappers. Provenance: ms. marginalia, emendations and underscoring.
- Regiomontanus, Joannes, 1436-1476. Epytoma Ioa[n]nis de Mo[n]te Regio in Almagestu[m] Ptolomei. Venetijs: Iohannis Ha[m]man de Landoia, dictus Hertzog ..., 1496 currente pridie Cale. Septembris [31 Aug.], Call No. Barchas Collection KA1496 .R4 F; [216] p.: ill.; 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 427 (IB.23380). Goff (rev.) R-111. Hain 13806*. Horblit, H.D. Grolier 100 science books, 89. ISTC, ir00111000. Rhodes 1506.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Without the letter of Abiosi. Binding: full vellum, with fold-over front edges. Provenance: Teodoro Becu (bookplate); ms. annotations. Par. marks and initial strokes added in red up to p. [26].
- Schedel, Hartmann, 1440-1514. Uniform Title: Liber chronicarum. German Title: Das Buch der Croniken vnnd Geschichten mit Figuren vnd Pildnussen von Anbeginn der Welt biss auff dise vnsere Zet. Short title: Nuremburg chronicle Augsburg: Durch Han[n]sen Schnsperger, im Jahr nach Cristi geburt. M.cccc.xcvj. am xviij Tag des Herbstmonats [18 Sept. 1496], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1496 .S315 f; CCCxxii [i.e. 317], [15] leaves: ill., maps, ports. (woodcuts); 30 cm.
  Notes: A "pirated" edition issued by Johann Schnsperger. "It had 2,165 illustrations [by Wolgemut, Pleydenwurff, and Durer] copied from the Nuremberg blocks and re-cut in smaller size. In none of his colophons did Schnsperger mention the name of the author [Schedel] or the translator [George Alt]".--Wilson, Adrian. The making of the Nuremberg chronicle, 1976, p. 191; pp. 193ff.
  References: BN cat. des incun., S-164. Goff (rev.), S-310. Hain 14511. ISTC (RLIN), is00310000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: some coloring in brown ink of illustration on a2v. Imperfect: lacks 2K6 (blank? cf. Hain 14511), 2L1-2L2 (map of Germania? cf. Hain 14511), and 3chi6 (blank?). Leaf Clxxx (K6) severely mutilated; the missing text and illustration supplied in ms. Binding error: leaf Clxiiii misbound after CClvii; leaf CClviii misbound after CClxiii. Binding: half white paper, marbled boards. Binder's title: Nuremburg Chronicle. Provenance: Carleton E. Byrne (signature); William J. Druecker (ink- stamp); remnants of red wax stamp on t.p.; ms. marginalia (some loss due to trimming); underscoring.
- Suetonius, ca. 69-ca. 122. Suetonius Tranquillus: cum Philippi Beroaldi et Marci Antonii Sabellici commentariis.... Venetiis ...: Per Simonen cognomento Beuilaqua, Papiensem, anno Christianae salutis 1496., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1496 .S84 F; [708] p. (the last leaf blank); 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 521 (IB.23965). Goff (rev.), S-827. Hain-Copinger 15128. ISTC (RLIN), is00827000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: calf; gilt decorations on upper and lower covers; panelled spine. Binder's title: Suetonii. Provenance: minor underscoring.
- Thomas, Aquinas, Saint, 1225?-1274. Prima [-tertia] pars Su[m]me Sancti Thome de Aquino Doctoris Angelici de Ordine Predicatorum. In imp[er]iali ciuitate Nurnberg no[n] sine exacta diligentia impressa: Per Anthoniu[m] Koberger, anno Incarnate Deitatis 1496 die xv mensis Ianuarij., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1496 .T53 f; 4 v.; 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 441 (IB.7500). Copinger 566. Goff (rev.), T-196. Hain 1436. Hain 1457. Hain-Copinger 1436. ISTC (RLIN), it00196000. Pellechet 1035.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials, initial strokes and paragraph marks in red or blue or red and blue. Binding: boards; no backing on spine; holes for clasps; ms. waste used. Provenance: ms. marginalia.
- Villadiego, Gonzalo. Ad illustrissimam Reginam Hispanie tractatus contra hereticam prauitatem per Gundissaluum de Villadiego sacri palacij apostolici auditorem editus incipit feliciter. [Incipit tractat[us] De irregularitate vtile ac necessariu[m] pro clericis per eunde[m] doctorem] Impressum Salmantice: Per Leonardu[m] Alemannm [sic] [et] per Fratrem Lupum Sanz de Nauarra Socios, vi. idus Januarij [8 Jan.] anno Domini 1496., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1496 .V55 f; [80] p.; 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., X, pp. 54-55 (IB.52862) Goff (rev.), G-729. ISTC, ig00729000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Variant to BM 15th cent. (IB.52862): "Et" precedes "Impressum Salmantice ..." in colophon. Imperfect: lacks a1 (blank). Binding: brown morocco, rectangular panel with flower at each corner on upper and lower covers. Binder's title: Villadiego (G)--Contra hereticam pravitatem et De irregularitate-- Salamanca, 1496.
- Anselm, Saint, Archbishop of Canterbury, 1033-1109. Opuscula Beati Anselmi Archiepiscopi Ca[n]tuarie[n]sis Ordinis Sancti Benedicti.[Basel: Johann Amerbach, not after 1497], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1497 .A57; [416] p. (last p. blank); 22 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent. III, p. 759 (IA.37512). GW 2033. Goff (rev.), A-761. Hain-Copinger, 1136. ISTC (RLIN), ia00761000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials and underscoring in red. Binding: half blind-stamped pigskin, beveled wooden boards, with clasp. Guards with rubricated Latin manuscript text bound in at front and back. Spine title: Anselmi opuscula. In box, with spine title: Opera. Provenance: W.A. Harding, Madingley (booklabel); eleven lines of annotations on t.p. signed by Fridericus Christophorus Dylbaum; Bibl. Publ. Basileensis (ink-stamp); Imper: Mon[aste]rij SS. Udal: et Afra (inscription).
- Aristotle. Ton en tede te biblo periechomenon onomata kai taxis = Eorum quae hoc uolumine continentur nomina ordo. Excriptum Venetiis: Manu stamnea i[n] domo Aldi Manutii Romani, graecorum studiosi, mense Februario M.III D. [Feb. 1497], Call No. Barchas Collection KA1497 .A75 f; [32], 268 leaves; 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 556 (IB.24431). Goff (rev.), A-959. GW 2334. ISTC, ia00959000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Imperfect: lacks leaves 265-66 (K3.4). Binding: half calf, brown marbled boards; edges red yellow. Binder's title: Aristotelis et Theophrastes opera. Aldus, Venice, 1497.
- Cleonides. Hoc in uolumine haec opera continentur: Cleonidae Harmonicum introductorium / interprete Georgio Valla Placentino. L. Vitruuii Pollionis De architectura libri decem. Sexti Iulii Frontini De aquaeductibus liber unus. Angeli Policiani opusculum, quod Panepistemon inscribitur. Angeli Policiani in priora analytica praelectio cui titulus est Lamia. Impressum Venetiis: Per Simonem Papiensem dictum Biuilaquam, anno ab Incarnatione 1497, die tertio Augusti., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1497 .C54 F; [188] p.: diagrams (woodcuts); 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 522 (IB.23973). GW 7123. Goff (rev.), C742. Hain-Copinger 5451. ISTC (RLIN), ic00742000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Binding: full green leather; title label on spine: Cleonidas Vitruvius, Frontinus, Policianus, Venetiis. Gathering b* bound preceding 2a*. In box, with spine title: Cleonides.
- Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321. Danthe Alighieri fiorentino. Impressa in Venetia: Per Piero de Zuanne di Quarengii da Palazago Bergamasco, del. M.CCCC.LXXXXVII. Adi. XI. octubrio. [11 Oct. 1497], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1497 .D36 f; [10], CCXCVII, [1] leaves: ill. (woodcuts); 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 513 (IB.24171). GW 7972. Goff (rev.), D-35. Hain-Copinger 5953. ISTC (RLIN), 00035000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: full red morocco, gilt panels on covers and spine; all edges gilt. Binder's title: Danthe. Provenance: Lon Gruel (bookseller's label); Giorgio Di Veroli (booklabel); Giorgio Fanan (bookplate); Di Francisc[o?] [] 1740 (inscription with ink-stamp seal).
- Ficino, Marsilio, 1433-1499. Uniform title: Epistolae Marsilii Ficini Florentini. Title: Marsilii Ficini epistolae.[Nuremberg]: Per Antonium Koberger impraesse, 1497, 24 Februarii., Call No. Barchas Collection KA1497 .F5; [10], CCXLIII, [1] (blank) leaves; 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 443 (IA.7529). Goff (rev.) F-155. GW 9874. Hain 7062*. ISTC, if00155000. Rhodes 775.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Binding: half white pigskin, marbled boards; morocco title label on spine. Binder's title: Marsilii Ficini Epistolae M.CCCC.XCVII. Imperfect: lacks leaves XCI-XCIV (M3-6). Provenance: Jo. Bapt. Galanti J.C. (inscription); underscoring and ms. marginalia.
- Grosseteste, Robert, 1175?-1253. Commentaria Roberti Linconie[n]sis in libros posteriorum Aristotelis cum textu seriatim inserto. Scriptu[m] Gualterii Burlei super eosdem libros posteriorum. Impresse Venetiis: Per Magistrum Otinum Papiensem, anno Domini 1497 die 22 Martii [22 March 1497], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1497 .G76; [76] p.; 27 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent, V, p. 568 (IB.24587). Goff (rev.), R-205. Hain-Copinger 10107. ISTC (RLIN), ir00205000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: white wrappers. Provenance: extensive ms. marginalia, some trimmed; ink drawing of soldier on t.p. verso; corrections to text in brown ink.
- Iamblichus, ca. 250-ca. 330. Index eorum, quae hoc in libro habentur--Iamblichus De mysteriis Aegyptiorum, Chaldaeorum, Assyriorum ... Venetiis: In aedibus Aldi, mense Septembri 1497., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1497 .I36 F; [372] p. (last 2 blank); 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent, V, p. 557 (IB.24446). BN cat. des incun., J-147 (add.). BN cat. des incun., J-147. Goff (rev.), J-216. Hain-Copinger 9358. ISTC (RLIN), ij00216000. Polain 2236.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials and paragraph marks in red and blue throughout; illuminated initial on leaf a2r. Binding: black morocco; panelled spine. Binder's title: De mysteriis. Provenance: Charles D. Brereton (armorial bookplate); leaves have ms. numbers 1-194 (nos. 81-89 omitted in numbering); ms. marginalia. Variants: leaf a1r, l. 13, reads de Platonis difinitionibus; leaf a2 is signed aii; leaf K2r, last word is spelled absente; catch words on leaves f8v and 7v do not match the first word on the following leaves.
- Melber, Johannes, 15th cent. Vocabularius predicantium.[Strasbourg: Georg Husner, 1497?], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1497 .M45; [344] p.; 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., I, p. 146 (IA.1981). Goff (rev.), M-469. Hain-Copinger, 11034. ISTC (RLIN), im00469000.